"How Much Licorice Is Safe?"
The three ways to alleviate the
fattening effects of stress are:
#1: treat the cause
by alleviating the stress.
If that's not possible,
you can #2,
modify your diet
to lower the production
of the adrenal stress hormone
cortisol,
as I describe in my video
on the effect of animal protein
on adrenal function.
And if all else fails,
you can #3,
try to block the effects
of cortisol on our fat cells.
If you drip cortisol
onto fat samples
taken deep inside people
undergoing abdominal surgery,
you can accelerate the formation
and growth of new fat cells.
But you can
disrupt this process
with a compound
that blocks the enzyme
that activates cortisol
in body fat.
The compound is called
glycyrrhetinic acid,
which is what
our gut bacteria make
and ferry into our bloodstream
when we eat glycyrrhizin.
Any guess as to where in our
diet glycyrrhizin is found?
I'll give you a hint: it derives
from the Greek words glykos,
meaning sweet,
and rhiza, meaning root.
We may be able to block some
of the effects of cortisol
in our body fat
when we eat licorice.
What works to slim
fat cells in a petri dish
or mice in a lab
may not work in a person,
but the licorice compound
appears to work
even when just
applied to the skin.
Researchers in Italy tried
rubbing the licorice compound
on women's thighs to see if it
would help with cellulite.
After a month of application,
the thickness of the superficial
fat layer on their thighs,
as measured by ultrasound,
was significantly reduced.
The reason we know it wasn't
just due to massaging it in
is because there was no change
on the control thigh
or among the women
that rubbed on placebos.
The difference was
only a few millimeters,
but the researchers
suggested it could be
a "gentler alternative
to cosmetic surgery."
What about eating licorice
or drinking licorice tea?
Dozens of trials
have been published
on the effects of various
licorice preparations
on weight loss,
and overall there's
just a small effect--
about a pound of extra weight
loss over a month or two
compared to placebo.
One reason it may not be higher
is that licorice causes you to
lose body fat but retain water.
Check this out.
After 2 months on licorice,
no change in overall weight--
but the women dropped
their percentage fat mass
by nearly 3 percent,
at the same time, though,
increasing their water retention
by about the same amount.
Then when they stopped
the licorice,
they lost the water,
but gained back the fat.
Licorice can cause you
to burn so much fat,
the surface of your abdomen
heats up a degree
within an hour of consumption,
but it has the opposite effect
on cortisol in your kidneys,
which, it turns out,
is actually a problem.
In body fat,
licorice blocks an enzyme
that activates cortisol;
but in our kidneys, licorice
blocks a different enzyme
that deactivates cortisol,
causing your kidneys to hold on
to extra water and sodium
and to lose potassium.
If you lose too much potassium,
it can cause weakness
and abnormal heart rhythms,
which is why the FDA sent out
a consumer advisory warning:
"If you're 40 or older,
eating 2 ounces
of black licorice a day
for at least two weeks
could land you in the hospital
with an irregular
heart rhythm.
No matter what your age,
don't eat large amounts
of black licorice at one time.
If you have been eating
a lot of black licorice
and have
an irregular heart rhythm
or muscle weakness,
stop eating it immediately
and contact your
healthcare provider."
Just because licorice is one
of the oldest and most popular
herbal medicines in the world
doesn't mean it's safe to eat
in large amounts
The retention
of fluid and sodium
can lead to blood pressure
elevation
eating less than two ounces
of licorice a day.
The regular consumption
of just a few ounces a day
can land you in the hospital
in a coma
with a blood pressure
of 200/140.
As many as 3 percent
of hospitalizations
due to high blood pressure
are caused by licorice.
Those with hypertension
should probably avoid
licorice completely,
as should pregnant women,
as licorice use
during pregnancy
is associated
with preterm delivery
and infant cognitive
dysfunction.
For nonpregnant individuals
with normal blood pressure,
what would be a safe dose?
The problem is
glycyrrhizin levels vary
in different licorice products
and some people are more
sensitive than others.
Now, a lot of licorice
sold in the US
doesn't even have
any true licorice,
and is instead
artificially flavored
or cut with anise oil.
So, ironically, it's the
black licorice you might find
at a natural food store
that may pose
the greatest concern.
Including
a broad safety factor,
the European Scientific
Food Committee suggests
regular consumption
of no more than 6 grams
of genuine licorice candy a day.
A Hershey-funded study
found that
"hard-coated licorice candies"
have 0.06 mg/g.
Presuming that's referring
to Good & Plenty,
the limit would be
about a box a day.
Licorice tea allows you
to access the herb
without all the crap in candy,
but a study of 33 brands
found such varying
levels of glycyrrhizin
that the safe daily dose
ranges from just
a tenth of a cup
up to 20 cups a day.
A life-threatening
arrhythmia reported
in a case entitled
"Dying for a cup of tea"
was in a woman who was
drinking 15 bags a day.
Based on the average level,
a half a cup of licorice tea
should be safe for most people,
though it's not clear
that would be enough
to have a fat-reducing effect,
which is why licorice
never made it into my book
"How Not to Diet."
Finally, cortisol
isn't the only steroid hormone
licorice can muck with.
It also interferes with
the production of testosterone.
Feed men the equivalent of
about 50 boxes of Good & Plenty,
9 ounces of black licorice,
or just a tablespoon of
licorice root powder every day,
and they experience
a 44 percent drop
in testosterone levels
within 4 days,
though blood levels bounced back
within 4 days of stopping.
The researchers suggest men
with high blood pressure
or decreased libido
should be questioned
about their licorice habits.